<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sentence of the Councell of VVarre, pronounced against the Lord Mountnorris, in Ireland the twelfth of December, 1635. VVith the Lord Mountnorris petition to the Parliament concerning his iniuries and wrongs sustayned by the Lord Deputy deceased.</title>
            <title>Sentence of warre pronounced against Sir Francis Annesley, Knight and Baron Mountnorris, in the realme of Ireland.</title>
            <author>Ireland. Army. Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92920</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2555</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E208_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17542</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860215</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860215</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112332</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92920)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112332)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 37:E208[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sentence of the Councell of VVarre, pronounced against the Lord Mountnorris, in Ireland the twelfth of December, 1635. VVith the Lord Mountnorris petition to the Parliament concerning his iniuries and wrongs sustayned by the Lord Deputy deceased.</title>
                  <title>Sentence of warre pronounced against Sir Francis Annesley, Knight and Baron Mountnorris, in the realme of Ireland.</title>
                  <author>Ireland. Army. Council.</author>
                  <author>Valentia, Francis Annesley, Viscount, 1585-1660. Humble petition of Sir Francis Annesley, Knight and Baron Mountnorris, in the realme of Ireland.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, 1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Valentia, Francis Annesley, --  Viscount, 1585-1660 --  Trials, litigation, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Strafford, Thomas Wentworth, --  Earl of, 1593-1641 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112332:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112332:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SENTENCE OF THE COVNCELL OF WARRE, PRONOVNCED AGAINST THE LORD
MOVNTNORRIS, IN <hi>JRELAND</hi> THE Twelfth of <hi>December,</hi> 1635. VVith
the Lord <hi>Mountnorris</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition to the Parliament concerning his
Iniuries and wrongs ſuſtayned by the Lord DEPVTY deceaſed.</p>
            <p>Printed in the yeare, 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:112332:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:112332:2"/>
            <head>BY THE LORD DEPVTIE <hi>WENTWORTH</hi> and Generall of the
Armie and Councell of <hi>VVarre.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Whereas the Kings moſt excellent majeſtie by his highnes
letters of the one and thirtieth of <hi>July</hi> laſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to vs the
Lord deputie, hath beene graciouſly pleaſed to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie that as he
ſhall ever expect that all due reverence ſhall be given by his ſubjects
to the perſon whome he appointeth to be his deputie, and generall of his
Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie within this his Kingdome of <hi>Jreland;</hi> So on the contrary, hee
ſhall hold them blame-worthie, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally being perſons who have
received their dignities from him, or hold their places of honor and truſt
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his governement. And yet ſhall forget there due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that way in their
words, or actions, to the ill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of others: And taking notice of the
carriage of the Lord <hi>Mountnorris</hi> his Majeſties Vice-treaſurer, and
Treaſurer at Warrs here (whoe holdes a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines place in his Majeſties
Armie) by uttering <pb n="4" facs="tcp:112332:3"/> ſome ſpeeches, inciting a revenge
vpon vs the Lord deputie and generall, from, a Liuetenant of this Armie, for
performing the duties of our place, with modeſty and good reaſon, in the
time of excerciſing our troope, which his Majeſtie in his ſaid letters
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares to be an offence, much unbeſeeming the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie of a priuie
Counceller to vs the Lord deputie, and the dutie of a Captaine to his generall,
and not to be ſuffered in any well governed Armie where good diſcipline
muſt be the rule and ſquare of euery mans actions.</p>
            <p>And therefore being very ſenſible of the honor of Vs, his
deputie, and generall of his Armie; which may ſuffer herein, and be of ill
conſequence in the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, he hath by his ſaid letters willed and
comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Vs the Lord deputie and generall upon receipt of thoſe his letters
to call a councell of warre, and after a due examination, and proofe of thoſe
ſpeeches by the Lord <hi>Mountnorris,</hi> his Majeſties expreſſe will
and pleaſure is, that hee ſhould under goe and be lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſuch
cenſure as the ſaid councell ſhould im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon him, for the full
reparation of Vs his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putie and generall in that poynt, and that there be no
fayling in putting the ſame in due and ſpeedy exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</p>
            <p>In obedience to which his Majeſties command, Wee the Lord
deputie called a councell of warre, whoe being this day aſſembled, Wee the
Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putie in the preſence of the ſaid Lord <hi>Mountnorris</hi> did
charge him with this offence, that within 3. or 4. daies or thereabouts, after
the end of the Parliament, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mentioned at the Lord <hi>Chancellors</hi>
Table, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Wee the Lord deputie had diſſolved the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, 
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112332:3"/> being ſitting downe in the preſence Chamber, one of Our
ſervants in mooving a ſtoole happend to hurt our foot, then indiſpoſed
through an acceſſion of the gout, that one then preſent at the Lord
<hi>Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors</hi> table, then ſaid to the Lord <hi>Mountnorris</hi> being
there likewiſe, that it was <hi>Anſley</hi> his Lordſhips kinſman, and
one of our Lord deputie and generalls gentlemen-vſhers that had done it,
whereupon the Lord <hi>Mountnorris</hi> then publikely, and in a ſcornefull
contemptuous manner, anſwered <hi>perhapps it was done in revenge</hi> of
that publique affront which my Lord deputie had done him formerly, <hi>But he
hath a brother that would not take ſuch a revenge,</hi> which Charge being
ſo laid, the Lord <hi>Mountnorris</hi> was required by this councell of
warre, to make anſwer thereunto, who going about to anſwer it, and yet
neither confeſſing nor denying them; This councell (after ſome time
ſpent therein) required him to anſwer the ſaid charge, either negatively
or affermatively, yet would not confeſſe or deny them. Wherevpon the
witneſſes vouched for profe thereof, were called, namely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who
though they were not the orginall relators of his Lordſhips, ſaid
diſcourſe to Vs the Lord depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, yet being preſent when the words were
ſo ſpoken, were conceive to be able to give teſtimony therein: And
therfore were called to be interrogated with all, thereupon, who being examined
before this councell upon oath, miniſtered unto them by the Clarke of the
councell before Vs by commandement of Vs the Lord deputie and their
depoſitions then reduced to writing, and ſubſcribed by them in our
preſence and in the preſence alſo of the ſaid L. <hi>Mountnorris,</hi>
who heard them affirme the ſame. It thereby appeareth that the 
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112332:4"/> ſaid Lord <hi>Mountnorris</hi> vttered and ſpoke the
ſaid words, in manner and forme, and at the time and place aforeſaid; The
charge laid againſt him ſtanding then fully proved, the ſaid Lord
<hi>Mountnorris</hi> at laſt ſubmitted himſelfe to the Iudgement of this
councell, proteſting that what interpretation ſoever his words might have
put vpon them, he intended noe preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice or hurt to the perſon of Vs the
deputie and generall, affirming that by theſe words, <hi>but he hath a
brother that would not take ſuch a revenge</hi> his Lordſhip meant onely
that he the ſaid brother would dye, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he would give Vs the deputie and
generall occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to give him ſuch a rebuke.</p>
            <p>Wee fell in the next place to conſider as of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the
offence, ſo of the puniſhement due there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto. And firſt for the nature
of the offence, Wee conceive it to containe firſt a calumnie againſt the
perſon of Vs the deputie and generall of the Armie, inſinuating by theſe
words the publike affront or the diſgrace which my Lord deputie had done him
for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, that indeede there had beene ſuch an affront, or diſgrace put
vpon him, by Vs the Lord deputie; whereas in truth it was nothing ſo, but
that which was pretended by the Lord <hi>Mountnorris</hi> to have been the
ſaid diſgrace or affront to his kinſman was this, that his ſaid
kinſman being one of the horſe-troope commanded by Vs the L. deputie in the
time of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing the ſaid troope, was out of order on horſe backe to
the diſturbance of the reſt then in exerciſing, for which the L. deputie
in a mild manner reproving him, as ſoone as Wee returned a ſide from him,
Wee obſerved him to laugh and geere Vs for Our juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe of him, which
Wee diſliking returned to him, <pb n="7" facs="tcp:112332:4"/> and laying a ſmall Caine
(which Wee then carried) on his ſhoulders (yet without any blow or ſtroake
then given him therewith) told him, that if hee did ſerve Vs ſo any more,
Wee would laie him over the pate, the truth of which facte appeared vnto Vs by
the relation of his Majeſties ſaid deputie and our generall, avowed and
confirmed by two of vs the Captaines, namely the Lord <hi>Kirkudbright,</hi>
and Sir <hi>Frederick Hamilton</hi> knight who then ſaw the manner of it, and
now ſate as members of this councell, which ſaid act was by this whole
councell adjudged to have beene a farr milder proceeding with the ſaid
<hi>Anſley,</hi> then ſuch an inſolence and diſobedience to any
Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, much more to his gennerall merited.</p>
            <p>And therefore it was a ſpeech ſavouring doubtles of malice, to
in ſinuate that as an affront or diſgrace which was indeed a iuſtly
merrited, but a mild and modeſt reprehention and admonition.</p>
            <p>Secondly Wee conceive the offence to containe an incitement to a
revenge in theſe words <hi>but hee has a brother that would not take ſuch a
Reuenge,</hi> which incite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment might have given encouragement to the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
being then and now in this kingdome, and Liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant of the ſaid L.
<hi>Mountnorris</hi> his foote companie to the ſaid <hi>Anſley</hi>
himſelfe being continually ſo neere the perſon of Vs the deputie and
generall, or to ſome other to have taken vp reſolutions of dangerous
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, and the manner of ſpeaking the words doe ſo farr aggravate
them, as there is no place left for any indulgent conſtruction to bee made of
them, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede any conſtruction, but ſuch as renders the ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker a
delinquent in a high and a tranſendent manner againſt the perſon of his
generall, and his Majeſties <pb n="8" facs="tcp:112332:5"/> authoritie whence we derive
Our power; This coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell alſo tooke it into conſideration, that if the
like words had beene ſpoken of the ſacred perſon of our dread Soveraigne
Lord the King, they had a mounted to little leſſe then high treaſon,
which by ſome rule of relation apply themſelves even to his Majeſtie,
being directed to the perſon of his deputie and the revenge thus inſolently
voted to have beene taken vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him: being done, when Wee the deputie, and
generall had that great and high honor which We alwayes eſteeme our Selfe in
our ſelfe farre vnworthy of, as to be apparralled and robed with his
Majeſties owne robe of majeſtie, and Soveraingnity: We conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
likewiſe the time when theſe words were ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken when part of the Armie
was in motion, and when there were divers companies of foote and troops of
horſe in the towne, &amp; daily in exerciſing, and training whereat for the
moſt part, We the deputie were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and the towne full of people from
all parts of the kingdome as then vnreturned back to their owne dwellings, from
their ſitting in Parliament.</p>
            <p>In the next place for the puniſhment due to his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, We
judge it to be an apparent breach and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the 41. Article of the
printed lawes and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of warr eſtabliſhed for the good conduct of the
ſervice of <hi>Ireland,</hi> dated the 13. of <hi>March</hi> 1633. and
publiſhed in print by Vs the Lord deputie ſoone af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our acceſſe to
this governement in theſe words of the ſaid article, <hi>No man ſhall
give any diſgracefull words or commit any act to the diſgrace of any
perſon in his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, or garriſon, or any part thereof vpon paine of
impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, publique diſarming and baniſhement from the Armie, as men
for ever diſabled to carrie Armes.</hi> And <pb n="9" facs="tcp:112332:5"/> which is more
in like breach and contempt of the 13. Article of the ſaid printed lawes and
orders of Warre, the words of which Article are theſe, <hi>No man ſhall
of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any violence or contemptuouſly diſobey his Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or doe any
Act, or ſpeake any words which are like to breede any mutiny in the Army or
Gariſon, or impeach the obeying of the generall or principall officers
directions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on paine of death;</hi> which Articles are no other then very
ſame Articles, this Army had allwaies been the governed by in the time of the
late Lord <hi>Faulkland,</hi> Lord <hi>Willm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tt,</hi> and other the generalls before them. And therefore this
Councell of Warre in conformity to his Majeſties gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ious pleaſure as aforeſaid, and aſwell to vindicate
the honour of his Majeſties deputy, and generall of his Army, from the wrong
and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, under which we now ſuffer, to the ſcandall of this
Govenement, and to ill example of others: As alſo to deliver one to all,
which beare office, or are liſted as members of the Army under the rule and
govenment of us his generall; An example of Juſtice for them to take warning
by, how they preſume to offend againſt the Authority intruſted us by his
Majeſtie doe hereby Adjudge, Order, and Decree, that the ſaid Lord
<hi>Mountnorris</hi> ſtands juſtly and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly lyable to undergoe the
cenſures, paires and puniſhments by the ſaid 41. Article and 15. Articles
proved againſt the breakers of all good diſcipline, and the
tranſgreſſors againſt thoſe orders which are by the ſaid 41.
Articles impriſonment, publique diſarming and baniſhment from the Army,
as a man for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ver diſable to carry
Armes: And by the ſaid 13. Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle death, And therefore according to the
ſaid Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, <pb n="10" facs="tcp:112332:6"/> this Councell doe unamimouſly with one
joynt conſent, not one of us being of other opinion) adjudged the ſaid Lord
<hi>Mountnorris</hi> for his ſaid high and great offences to bee impriſoned
to ſtand from henceforth deprived of all the places, with the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments
due thereunto, which he holds now in the Army, to be diſarmed, to be
baniſhed the Army, and diſ-inabled for ever bearing office therein
hereafter: And laſtly, to be ſhot to death, or to looſe his head, at the
pleaſure of the Generall: Given at his Majeſties Caſtle of
<hi>Dublin</hi> the 12. day of <hi>December,</hi> 1635.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentia.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi> Tho. Cromwell</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi> R. Ranelagh.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi> R. Dillon.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi> Law. Eſmond.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi> Kirkudbright.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi> Iohn Barlaſſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi> Charles Coot.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi> Tho. Wenman.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi> Arthur Terringham.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi> Arthur Blundell.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi> Faith: Forteſcue.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi> Ro. Farrar.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi> Io. Borlaſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi> Tho. Roper.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:112332:6"/>
            <head>TO THE HONORABLE AS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly the Knights, Citizens, and
Burgeſſes of the Commons houſe of <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The humble Petition of Sir <hi>Francis
Annſley,</hi> Knight and Baron. <hi>Mountnorris</hi> in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the
Realme of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>Humbly ſhewing,</opener>
            <p>THat whereas your Petitioner for divers yeares hath beene imployed
by his Majeſtie and his late Royall Father in divers Offices and imployments
of great truſt and eminence within the Realme of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> wherein
to the uttermoſt of his power hee hath Faithfully diſcharged the truſt in
him repoſed with the publique approbation, and ſatisfaction both of this,
and that State and Realme; in Teſtimony where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, his Majeſtie was
pleaſed to dignifie your Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner with the ſtile he now beares, yet the
Right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Thomas</hi> Earle of <hi>Strafford,</hi> Lord Livetenant
of the ſaid Realme of <hi>Ireland</hi> having conceived a cauſeleſſe
diſtruſt againſt your Petitioner, and thereupon indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voring the revenge
of ſome perſonall neglects, and the undue advancement of his own ends and
inſtruments, by the diſhonour and ruine of your Petitioner, his Lordſhip
without any juſt cauſe at all, not onely ſtript and deprived your
Petitoner of thoſe honorable im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments <pb n="12" facs="tcp:112332:7"/> with contumely
and reproach, but alſo of his owne private fortunes, and the birthright and
li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of a ſubject, a ſhort viewe of part, of which your Petitioners
ſufferings, he humbly preſents in theſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing particulars.</p>
            <div n="1" type="subpart">
               <head>1.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> whereas his late Majeſtie King
<hi>Iames</hi> by his Highneſſe Letters bearing date the firſt day of
<hi>October</hi> in he 14. yeare of his Majeſties Reigne, did appoint your
Petitioner to be one of the principall Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and of the Councell of
State for that Realme; whereupon your Petitioner was ſworne and admitted
accordingly: and whereas after <hi>viz.</hi> the eighth day of <hi>Iune</hi> in
the 16. yeare of the ſaid Majeſties Raigne, his ſaid late Majeſtie by
his Letters Patents under the great Seale of <hi>Ireland,</hi> did grant unto
your Petitioner aſwell a Penſion of 200. pound <hi>per Annum,</hi> for the
everciſe of the ſaid office, together with the Fees thereunto belonging, as
alſo the office of the Privie Signet, with the incidents thereunto, to bee
held by your Petitioner during his life, immediately after the death
ſurrender or forfeiture of Sir <hi>Dudley Norton,</hi> who had the ſame
office and penſion during his life, by force of which premiſſes as your
Petitioner faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully executed the ſaid office of a Secretary, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fee
during the life of the ſaid Sir <hi>Dudley Norton,</hi> who was then for many
yeares infirme and unable to exerciſe the ſame, ſo he ought to hold the
ſaid office and pention ſince his deceaſe or ſurrender, according to
the office of his Majeſties ſaid Patent; Yet upon pretenſe of a
diſcour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſie ſuppoſed to bee
done by your Petitioner to his Lordſhips brother Sir <hi>George 
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:112332:7"/> Wentworth,</hi> his Lordſhip obtained a ſurrender to
bee made by the ſaid Sir <hi>Dudley Norton</hi> in or about the 12. day of
<hi>July</hi> in the 10. yeare of his now Majeſties Raigne, and contrary to
all right and juſtice procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the ſaid office and Fees to bee conferred
upon Sir <hi>Phillip Manwareing,</hi> who notwithſtanding your Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners
often requeſt and Petitions to his Lordſhip for releife, ſtill holds the
ſame under protection of the power and greatneſſe of his Lordſhip.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="subpart">
               <head>2.</head>
               <p>Whereas his Majeſtie by his Highneſſe Letters Patents
bearing date the 30. day of <hi>May</hi> in the firſt yeare of his
Highneſſe Raigne, did appoint your Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioner to be his Uice Treaſurer
and generall Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of his Revenewes within the ſaid Realme of
<hi>Jre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> during his Majeſties pleaſure, with the Fees and profits
thereunto belonging, and appointed your Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioner to bee Treaſurer of
warres in the ſaid King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome by his Majeſties Letters of the 13. of
<hi>June</hi> 1632. <hi>And whereas</hi> your Petitioner did refuſe at his
ſollicitation to make a diſhonorable ſale of the ſaid offices, the
ſaid Earle being therewith enraged, and thereupon indeavoring to captivate
not onely your Petitioners ſaid offices, but alſo his honour and life to
his Lordſhips power and pleaſure; his Lordſhip in a time of publique
peace and ſerenity within that Realme the 12. day of <hi>December</hi> 1635.
did call a Councell of warre, and did accuſe your Petitioner of ſome words
ſuppoſed to be ſpoken by your Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner many moneths before, tending in
his Lordſhips ſtrayned conſtructions to the diſturbance of goven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, 
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112332:8"/> and without allowing your Petitioner liberty of clearing
his innocency in a legall manner, or ſo much as an houres time, to make his
juſt defence, proceeded to ſentence at the ſame time, and although the
ſaid ſuppoſed words were no waies criminall, yet his Lordſhip contrary
to all juſtice, did cauſe the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of death to be procured againſt
your Petitioner being a Peere of that Realme, as by the Copie of the ſaid
ſentence hereunto annexed may appeare.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="subpart">
               <head>3.</head>
               <p>Though his Lordſhip for the further advancing of his owne
ends, did partly forbeare the execution of the ſaid ſentence, yet by colour
thereof his Lordſhip forthwith diſpoſed of your Petitioners foot
compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and committed your Petitioner priſoner to the Caſtle of
<hi>Dublin,</hi> where he was continued from the ſaid 12. of
<hi>December</hi> 1635. untill the 16 day of <hi>Aprill</hi> 1637. and within
that time your Petitioners papers, Cabinets, Trunkes, and other places of his
houſe were ſtrictly ſearched by ſome of his greateſt Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries
by his Lordſhips direction, and your Petitioner for the ſpace of 20. dayes
was kept cloſe priſoner, to the extreame hazard of his life, untill at
laſt he was forced to purchaſe his liberty by ſubmiſſion to the
ſaid unjuſt and illegall ſentence, and by the accepting of a pardon for
the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="subpart">
               <head>4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </head>
               <p>His Lordſhip taking Advantage of your Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners condition
and indeavouring not onely to juſtifie <pb n="15" facs="tcp:112332:8"/> his former
proceedings, but alſo to convict your Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioner, and render him a
delinquent without a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, did iſſue a Commiſſion to
Commiſſioners of his owne choice and nomination, who during your
Petitioners impriſonment examined divers witneſſes touching ſome
miſdemeanors falſely charged upon your Petitioner in his office of
Vice-treaſurer, which being returned, and the effects thereof tranſmitted
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Kingdome, his Lordſhip by this and other un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due practiſes
brought your Petitioner into diſgrace with his Majeſtie, and thereupon
procured the ſaid Offices of Vice-treaſurer, Generall Receiver, and
Treaſurer of Warres to be conferred upon Sir <hi>Adam Loftus</hi> Knight, who
had beene formerly one of your Petitioners accuſers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="subpart">
               <head>5.</head>
               <p>Whileſt thus your Petitioner had his office taken from him,
his honour and integrity injuriouſly ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniated, his liberty reſtrained,
his life not onely ſubject to the mercie of the ſaid Earle, but extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
indangered by a continuall ſickeneſſe cauſed by his impriſonment by
his Lordſhip; not therewith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, cauſed an Information to bee
preferred againſt your Petitioner in the Caſtle Chamber, touching the
ſeverall ſuppoſed miſdemeanors enquired of the ſaid
Commiſſioners, wherein though your Petitioner no way conſcious of any
guilt, yet finding his counſell awed by his Lordſhips power, his Judges to
be ſuch as were formerly his Inquiſitors, the witneſſes pre-engaged by
an extrajudiciall examination, could expect no leſſe than a ſentence
againſt him notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his innocence, your Petitioner was put to this
miſerable choice, either to ſuffer continuance <pb n="16" facs="tcp:112332:9"/> and
addition to his miſeries, or otherwiſe to make ſuch ſubmiſſion as
his Lordſhip pleaſed, whereupon your Petitioner was enforced in an
ignominious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to make ſubmiſſion, hoping thereby to purchaſe his
Liberty and goe into <hi>England</hi> according to his Majeſties directions,
though by ſo doing he could not effect the ſame, but his impriſonment was
continued notwithſtanding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="subpart">
               <head>6.</head>
               <p>Whereas alſo by the fundamentall lawes of that Realme, as
alſo by his Majeſties Declaration publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in print upon the returne of
a Commiſſion &amp; by the advice of many grave &amp; wiſe
Commiſſiners ſent from hence into <hi>Ireland</hi> for the examination of
the greivances of his Majeſties ſubjects in that Realme, the Lord Deputie
&amp; Councell are not to meddle up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Titles of inheritance betweene party and
party, or in buſineſſe belonging to the Cognizance of other Courts or to
alter poſſeſſion, yet his Lordſhip upon a paper petition to him
preferred by <hi>Richard Rollſton</hi> againſt your Petitioner touching the
manner of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more</hi> in the
ſaid ſaid Realme after 18. yeares quiet poſſeſſion thereof by your
petitioner, hath Decreed the ſaid lands to the ſaid <hi>Rollſton,</hi>
and by his owne warrant removed your Petitioner out of poſſeſſion
thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="subpart">
               <head>7.</head>
               <p>Whereas alſo by the lawes of that Kingdome, and by the ſaid
declaration, proceedings before the Lord Deputy, and Councell for things
remediable in <pb n="17" facs="tcp:112332:9"/> other Courts by paper Petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; the
abuſes of <hi>Habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ascorpus</hi> within that Realme are prohibited, yet upon
a paper Petition preferred to his Lordſhip and the Councell by, one
<hi>Walter Peperd</hi> touching land of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance in the Petitioners
poſſeſſion, his Lordſhip hath retained the ſaid cauſe for his
hearing, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding your Petitioners legal exception thereunto: &amp;
upon the like paper Petition preferred to his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, by <hi>Arthur
Manwaring,</hi> his Lordſhip hath for divers yeares delayed and
fruſtratethed benefit of an execution which your Petitioner had againſt him
for a debt by bond, &amp; yet there is no end of the ſaid
<hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warings</hi> vexatious ſuites before his Lordſhip, and ſuch other
Referrees as his Lordſhip appoints.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="subpart">
               <head>(8)</head>
               <p>His Lordſhip rated your Petitioner for the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his
Majeſties Subſidies in one 1000 pound in the Kings bookes, whereas men of
farre greater viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and knowne eſtates are not Charged with halfe that
proportion, your Petitioners eſtate being very meane to ſupply the
condition and honours gratiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conferred upon him by his Majeſtie and
his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Father in acceptance of his Faithfull ſervices, and his wife and
eleven-children.</p>
               <p>Now for aſmuch as your Petitioner is no waies guilty of the
crimes, under which hee hath ſuffered, and yet it hath beene the height of
his Lordſhips en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, not onely to bereave your Petitioner of his honour
and fortunes, but alſo (as much as in him laie) of his innocencie, by the
ſaid extorted ſubmiſſion, and <pb n="18" facs="tcp:112332:10"/> obtruded pardon, he
here relinquiſheth all advantage by the ſaid pardon, and freely ſubmits
the crymes to him imputed to the ſcrutine and determination of this honorable
and impartiall aſſembly, and for aſmuch as the oppreſſions
ſuſtained by your Petitioner, doe not onely in the higheſt degree
concerne your Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner in his innocencie, liberty and fortunes, but alſo
tend to the publique abuſe and ſcandall of the lawes, liberties and
juſtice of both Realmes, and to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troducing an Arbitrary forme of
goverment, your Petitioner humbly offers the premiſſes to the
conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of this honorable aſſembly; and humbly prayes ſuch
reperation therein, as to this honorable aſſembly ſhall ſeeme to
ſtand wiih right and Iuſtice.</p>
               <closer>
                  <hi>And your Petitioner ſhall daily pray,
&amp;c.</hi>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
